Guide to the American Veterans for Peace Records TAM.246
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
American Veterans for Peace Records
Bulk, 1951-1955
1945-1957, (Bulk 1951-1955)
TAM.246
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
American Veterans for Peace was founded in 1951 to oppose American participation in the Korean War. The AVP opposed militarism, supported improved Soviet relations and a progressive social agenda. It published Progressive Veteran(later Vet's Voice). The collection includes: correspondence, ephemera, internal documents, petitions, public statements, and newsletters of the AVP and other progressive organizations.
American Veterans for Peace.
Box 1
Provenance
Gift of Stanley Turkel, 2001.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
American Veterans for Peace, officially founded in June 1951, was the result of a Communist Party-oriented initiative in the months following the outbreak of the Korean War that saw the founding of several local Veterans for Peace organizations. The AVP published a monthly newsletter, Progressive Veteran, 1949-1955 (title changed to Vet's Voice in 1950). While its main purpose was to oppose American participation in the Korean War, the AVP also opposed militarism, supported improved relations with the Soviet Union and a progressive social agenda.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is arranged alphabetically, and contains correspondence, ephemera, internal documents, petitions and public statements, and newsletters of the AVP, and of other progressive organizations, including foreign veterans organizations. There are files on two annual AVP events -- an art show, and Elbe River Day, commemorating the meeting of American and Soviet troops in 1945. Other files document Desert Fox(a campaign against the 1951 movie), the suppression (by the U.S. Post Office) of Vet's Voice, an allied organization, the American Women for Peace (including copies of two issues of its monthly newsletter, The Peacemaker), and the Australian Legion of Ex-Servicemen and Women.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into 1 series.
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
American Veterans for Peace.; Green, Paul, 1894-1981; Turkel, Stanley.; Wagner, Norman; Communism |z United States; Correspondence.; Documents.; Petitions.; Veterans |z United States.
- Container List
  - General
    - American Labor Party, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Legion. Duncan-Paris Post, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Peace Crusade, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American Veterans Committee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - American Veterans for Peace: National, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American Veterans for Peace: Origins, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Women for Peace, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Art Shows, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Australian Legion of Ex-Servicemen and Women, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: Foreign and United Nations, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence: Outgoing, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence: Received, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Desert Fox (movie) Campaign, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Elbe River Day, 1945-1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Freedom's War Gum, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Housing, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Korean Veterans, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Leaflets: Miscellaneous, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - New York Peace Institute, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - New York Veterans for Peace, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - New York Veterans for Peace: Leaflets, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Petitions, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Society for the Prevention of World War III, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Veterans' Organizations: Other, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Vet's Voice: Suppression of, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 25)